Guide to the Harvey Seymour Sussman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Harvey Seymour Sussman papers
1942-1995
MS 1457
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
The papers consist of correspondence, memorabilia, and photographs which document Harvey Seymour Sussman's year as a member of the Army Specialized Training Program (ASTP) at Yale University and his service as a member of the Office of Strategic Services. The papers also include material for the ASTP reunion at Yale in 1990 and a 1995 diary of a return visit to Burma.
Sussman, Harvey Seymour, 1923-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Harvey Sussman, 1986, 1989-1990, 2005, and 2006; Robin Winks, 1987; and Daniel C. O'Neil, 1990.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Harvey Seymour Sussman Papers consist of correspondence and memorabilia, which document Harvey Sussman's military service during World War II. The papers highlight his participation in the Army Specialized Training Program (ASTP) studying Malay at Yale University. Additional correspondence and memorabilia record Sussman's OSS assignments in the Far East and his travels through Europe and Asia on his way to this posting. Sussman's student years at Yale following the end of the war and his work as a Malay translator are also recorded in the papers. Harvey Sussman donated his papers to the Yale University Library in 1990, following a reunion of ASTP participants at which he exhibited many of these papers. Materials given to Sussman by other reunion participants supplement these papers.
The papers are arranged in two sections: Correspondence and Memorabilia. Correspondence includes Sussman's frequent letters to his family in Baltimore and later to his fiancée Muriel Hodes in New Haven. Sussman's letters from Camp Lee and from Yale describe the daily routine of a young Jewish soldier's life and detail the rigorous program of training for an ASTP participant. Though for security reasons he was not able to describe the work he was doing during his time in the Far East, Sussman's letters after his arrival are full of the daily details of military life.
Memorabilia includes announcements, programs, and course notes from the ASTP program at Yale, as well as playbills and invitations from the New Haven area. The section also includes military orders, travel brochures, postcards, and photographs from Sussman's assignments. Examples of Sussman's contract work as a Malay translator for the State Department are also in this section. Several files document Sussman's efforts to locate former ASTP members and to prepare a reunion at Berkeley College in May 1990. These files include correspondence with members and officials at Yale helping to organize the reunion, as well as programs and memorabilia from the reunion. The photographs include pictures of the ASTP participants and of colleagues on assignment in the Far East during World War II and photographs taken at the reunion. Printed materials of a conference dealing with the Office of Strategic Services is also included in the papers.
With his papers, Sussman also donated his short-snorter, a record of his military travels in currency, and other paper money and coins. These are now located in the Yale University Art Gallery's collection of Coins and Medals.
Biographical / Historical
Harvey Seymour Sussman was born in Brooklyn, New York, on October 3, 1923. His family later moved to Baltimore where he graduated from high school. He was inducted into the army in February 1943, and while in training at Camp Lee, Virginia, he was selected to study Malay in the Army Specialized Training Program (ASTP). From June 1943 to June 1944, he was stationed at Berkeley College on the Yale University campus where he took intensive language training. He was then sent to Washington to learn cryptography by the Office of Strategic Services (OSS).
Sussman served overseas with the OSS, first in England, and then in Burma and Ceylon, with other special assignments in the Far East. On his return to the United States in March 1946, Sussman married Muriel Anne Hodes. He returned to Yale University to complete a B.A. degree in oriental studies and graduated in February, 1948.
While at Yale and for a year after graduation, Sussman did Malay translation for the United States State Department. He entered the wholesale food business and eventually became president of Consolidated Brokers, Inc., a food brokering company in New Haven, Connecticut. Sussman died on December 16, 2010, in Delray Beach, Florida.
Espionage; Malay language -- Study and teaching; Military intelligence; World War, 1939-1945 -- Secret service; Burma; Sussman, Harvey Seymour, 1923-; United States. Office of Strategic Services; Army Specialized Training Program (U.S.); Berkeley College (Yale University); Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1943-1949, 1969, 1985-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 5)
    - Hodes, Muriel, 1944-1945 September (Box 1, Folder 6 - 8)
    - Sussman family, 1943 January-1944 April (Box 1, Folder 9 - 16)
    - Sussman family, 1944 May, July-1945 December (Box 2, Folder 17 - 33)
  - Memorabilia
    - ASTP: course notes [includes notebook of Malay language], 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 34 - 35)
    - ASTP: New Haven, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Military, 1944-1946 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Travel: England, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Travel, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Yale, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Malay translation work, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Malay translation work, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 42 - 43)
    - Reunion of ASTP
      - Planning papers, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - Responses from ASTP members, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Planning and concluding papers, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 46)
        General note
        See also: Folder 49
      - Responses and reminiscences of ASTP members, 1988-1991, undated (Box 4, Folder 46A)
    - "The Secrets War" [Office of Strategic Services conference materials], 1991 July 11-12 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous, 1942, 1943, 1946, 1960, 1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 47A)
  - Photographs, 1942-1945, 1989-1990, undated (Folder 5, Folder 48)
  - Oversize, 1990 (Folder 5, Folder 49)
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-139
  - Myanmar (Burma): chronicle of a return visit by veterans of Detachment 101, O.S.S. (added to Box 4), 1995